<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>COVEREDINBEES / A hive of TLDR &amp; villainy</title>
<link>https://coveredinbees.org/</link>
<atom:link href="https://coveredinbees.org/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>A hive of TLDR and villainy</description>
<generator>quarto-1.7.33</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 23:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Prototyping open econ tools</title>
  <link>https://coveredinbees.org/posts/open_econtools/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Over the past couple of years, I’ve been building up a loose ‘regional economics’ toolkit while digging into UK sectors, growth and other econ-adjacent data (working mainly with <a href="https://www.southyorkshire-ca.gov.uk/">SYMCA</a> wearing my <a href="https://y-pern.org.uk/">Y-PERN</a> hat)<sup>1</sup>.</p>
<p>I’m gathering data/code/explanations onto a <a href="https://danolner.github.io/RegionalEconomicTools/">regecontools website</a>, though bits are spread all over (this <a href="https://danolner.github.io/posts/outputs_livelist/">live outputs page</a> on the techie blog has gathered most of it in one place).</p>
<p>Over the next six months or so, I want to try and make this a more focused project. The plan is roughly this:</p>
<ul>
<li>Using open data/methods, test and improve these tools so they’re as useful as they can be.</li>
<li>Dig deeper into the ideas and questions we’re pursuing - iterate between these and the tools.</li>
<li>Build on existing relationships and search out new ones to prototype a better tools/ideas/questions cycle.</li>
<li>Help build capacity through things like <a href="https://vimeo.com/user99857619/review/1103090076/32e50123d2">this ONS Local session</a> I ran introducing R for regional economic analysis (<a href="https://danolner.github.io/RegionalEconomicTools/R_regecon_taster_2025_revealjs.html#/title-slide">the online slides here</a> work as a how-to guide, including how to use R easily in a browser).</li>
</ul>
<p>The least tested part of this for me, and maybe the most interesting, is the ‘tools/ideas/questions’ cycle. The tools/concepts we use to make sense of our regional economies have grown from a hodgepodge of ideas. These can be questioned at different levels - from narrowly methodological (“How much difference does it make to productivity if we exclude imputed rent? Do existing measures of public sector output capture their real value?”) to deeper, more political ideas about what economies are and what/who they’re for (see e.g.&nbsp;the <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-025-09385-1">latest doughnut economics Nature paper</a> or <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1470160X25010088?via%3Dihub#b0125">this survey</a> of over 200 eco-econs/wellbeing indicators).</p>
<p>Y-PERN’s whole purpose has been to experiment with breaking down barriers in this cycle - trying to push past <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Information_deficit_model">deficit model</a> thinking that just sees that cycle as a “transfer of information from experts to non-experts”. This is still a pretty entrenched view: academics toil in the dark for years, emerge pale and blinking, clutching new insights. A separate ‘knowledge exchange’ process then commences.</p>
<p>But that doesn’t align with the reality of data-driven policymaking: <em>everyone involved</em> are experts in what they do. It’s a deeply collaborative endeavour. We don’t all share the same knowledge, but we also won’t progress much without bringing everyone’s together.</p>
<p>The ‘open’ part of the toolkit is in symbiosis with the ‘ideas/questions’ part. Regions face many of the same economic questions, including identical asks from central government (e.g.&nbsp;to produce Local Growth Plans). The same data sources are re-used, the same assumptions. At the same time, we’re all working to develop our own identities as devolution deepens. Given that, here’s the philosophy I think we should be applying:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Do data work openly where we can. It will support collaboration and learning. It will help build a shared sense of ground truth. It will avoid wheel reinvention.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I don’t have a dogmatic fealty to open source — we have a data/analysis mixed economy where private providers can do things other can’t, and that’s a good thing. There are also essential datasets that can’t be open, for good reason. But <em>where we can</em>, working in the open just goes better with the grain of those three things: (1) collaborative learning/capacity building across silos; (2) developing our shared sense of ground truth; (3) avoiding wheel reinvention (a facet of <a href="https://www.ukrn.org/">reproducibility</a>, which needs open methods; you can’t reproduce something if you can’t access it).</p>
<p>The only way this works is if we prototype. Or call that <a href="https://www.bi.team/publications/test-and-learn-a-playbook-for-mission-driven-government/">test and learn</a> if you prefer. As that doc says:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>At its simplest [it] involves (1) developing something; (2) making contact with reality; (3) learning from the results.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Sounds great in principle - but we have to be open to our preconceptions being challenged when we smack into reality. The <a href="https://cdn.fastly.steamstatic.com/apps/valve/Valve_NewEmployeeHandbook.pdf">Valve Games employee manual</a> puts it like this<sup>2</sup>:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“—–ing up is a great way to find out that your assumptions were wrong or that your model of the world was a little bit off. As long as you update your model and move forward with a better picture, you’re doing it right. Look for ways to test your beliefs. Never be afraid to run an experiment or to collect more data.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>While not always comfortable, this is part of how to grow our shared sense of ground truth. It’s perfect ‘<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blind_men_and_an_elephant">blind people and elephant</a>’ parable territory<sup>3</sup>. Brace for an extremely mixed elephant/economy metaphor.</p>
<ul>
<li>We want to see as much of the elephant as we can. How is the economy structured, what’s growing, shrinking, changing? Why?</li>
<li>Those lead naturally to “What data/methods do we have to answer them?” Any one data source helps us grab a single pachyderm part. Multiple sources give us a grip on different bits, but the whole beast still eludes us. We need enough knowledge to know our tools’ limitations - we will regularly hit the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Streetlight_effect">streetlight effect</a>, mistaking the data for the whole animal<sup>4</sup>.</li>
</ul>
<p>Combining openness and prototyping, though, we can exchange what we think we’ve seen with others, maybe learn from our errors, and move a step or two closer to a collective sense of shape.</p>
<p>Then there are awkward people saying things like, “Are we <em>sure</em> this is an elephant? I think maybe we have to go back to first principles here.” But again - an open, testing approach lets us argue our competing pachyderm theories out, and often discover diverse tools can be used in different places very effectively despite no total agreement.</p>
<p>So, what next? I’ll need to keep things fairly narrow to achieve anything at all, most likely by testing some different basic ONS and Companies house economy measures, see what could be improved, what blind spots there are. I’ll also try to find two or three focused problems to apply this to - including, I’m hoping, something on how we close the gap between quant views of sector mix and ground level knowledge of how firms interact, and what difference that makes to their success.</p>
<p>Underlying-idea-wise, there’s a whole lot of prior technical change ideas that can help shed light on current AI fears (I’m also working on an AI impact project) and could help think through where we want economic progress to come from.</p>
<p>Let’s see how contact with reality changes things…</p>
<section id="cuttinz" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="cuttinz">CUTTINZ</h2>
<p>Not deny reality of austerity-hit LAs lack of bodies but can we move a few more notches to breaking down distinctions in the networks we make, getting past institutional diffs?</p>
<p>Experience has shown doing that has to start with people - those willing to work together on the same problems…</p>
<p>It wouldn’t be possible or wise to try and do all things econ-toolkit-wise (see e.g.&nbsp;this synthesis of inclusive econ measures; there are so many!)</p>
<p>Prototyping what this niche is What specific qualities these kinds of networks can bring and why they flow naturally from / are a good match for the direction of devolution</p>
<p>That last one covers both normative stuff and ‘theory of data / theory of change’ stuff.</p>
<p>But this is one of the things I want to experiment with. It’s a good time to try</p>
<p>because of the networks because of being able to create space for it Start with some humility - the world doesn’t have a shortage of people who’ll be willing to tell you they know The Answers.</p>
<p>Black box vs network [can mention some of the hollowing-out issues here that have no quick fix cf.&nbsp;Bradford community data]</p>
<p>What I think we have a chance to do collectively is a bit different - to create a shared sense of ground truth as we work together, built on the best understanding we can create between us.</p>
<p>(Also, these last two points are rarely so cleanly separated - back to that in a moment.)</p>
<p>Issues around avoiding data-driven questions, streetlight effect. Issue of developing our own internal model - not just infographic cf.&nbsp;x-ray What are we missing? What’s wrong with our data and methods?</p>
<p>The limitations here include: “you need to leave the house and talk to people.” This is the quant data / reality gap…</p>
<p>Then, somewhere in here: what do we want? That’s the normative stuff. Try to unpick examples here. E.g. assumptions around how to make everyone more wealthy are key there, right?</p>
<p>But open methods are more aligned with what I think is the reality of data-driven policymaking: everyone involved are experts in what they do. This is a deeply collaborative endeavour. We don’t all have the same knowledge, but we also won’t progress much without bringing everyone’s together. Contrast to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Information_deficit_model">deficit model</a>, which imagines a “transfer of information from experts to non-experts”. (This is a fairly common view of e.g.&nbsp;the university / policy relationship.)</p>
<p>Sometimes there’s straightforward transmission - if I’m teaching R coding methods to people who are new to it, say. But it’s never just that. I’ve seen this again and again in different settings - <a href="https://www.danolner.net/2019/02/sheffields-first-data-for-good-hack-day">here</a>, we bought some data skills but had little insight into what that Sheffield homelessness charity’s data actually meant. They made it make sense.</p>
<p>In regional policy, it’s been a little different but with the same outcome.</p>
<p>Two things, the above then also capacity building / why open methods = learning/collab = capacity building (I think)</p>
<p>You probably wouldn’t want collaborative heart surgery for example</p>
<p>Because it’s open, anyone can contribute, copy, re-use etc</p>
<p>So the more we build relationships and share tools and ideas, the better. Y-PERN’s helped grow the strength of those relationships in Yorkshire &amp; Humber</p>
<p>A lot of that groundwork has been done already through regional network building. We have a decent chance of getting a handle on a good two-thirds to three-quarters of the pachyderm.</p>
<p>The status of those last question types is tricky. As SYMCA’s Alice Rubbra eloquently explains <a href="https://y-pern.org.uk/blog/the-relationship-between-policymaking-and-research-how-it-works-sometimes/">here</a> on the Y-PERN blog, it’s a clash of wotsits</p>
<p>Remain tool agnostic, code, no-code. I’m an R person, others won’t be, and there are up and downsides to going that route. Thinking agnostically, I can still provide links to processed data sources that others can use, and provide easy-ish-to-run examples…</p>
<p>I’ve already seen the value of openness for my own process of getting from numbers to things-in-front-of-policymakers [frame better?]. But how to deepen the collaboration part?</p>
<p>The ‘shared ground truth’ thing has a couple of elements. I’ve heard more than once about data ‘black boxes’ that can result from some commissioned work. You get an analysis, but no access to the data and no way to really know how conclusions have been reached. It’s a one-time hit - once the commission’s done, you decide to either take the results on face value or not, and then have to re-commission if more is needed later. [ties to point above about this not being a purely client rel - about that ‘shared truth’ thing between us where data is one facet… oh I do say this below!]</p>
<p>Again — I’m not saying that can’t be valuable and necessary, as organisations can supply expert analyses that often can’t be done in-house. I also carry out that kind of interpretation.</p>
<p>Build on open data, make the tools, build the capacity, link people together, do it questioningly, allow ways to get to the root and feed that back into the policy cycle, “walk asking”.</p>
<p>There are reasons why data work can’t be done openly (datasets that contain private information) or won’t be done openly (data/methods are IP a firm earns its living from; researchers protecting a lovingly curated dataset). But in regional policy, and with the vast body of data the ONS among others hold, there’s plenty of scope for it.</p>
<p>This is in GVA post and should connect:</p>
<p>And then something on: why the orig data sources are not enough. Just supplying openly isn’t enough. Without capacity to see what’s in that data, you’re still blind. What exactly does that capacity look like and how do we build it?</p>
<p>More recently, I’ve been re-using these tools to help other Yorkshire government bodies get insights quickly. This came about quite serendipitously, but it’s helped convince me it’s a good way to work. [Explain something about how much it speeds things up / how cost effective it is]</p>
<p>(This is all on my github where I’m trying to corral more of it into the regionalecontools site, itself a github repo; the website’s all generated using R.)</p>
<p>I’m not suggesting how I’ve approached this is anything like the best way - but I am arguing that building these pipelines openly leads to good things that otherwise couldn’t happen. What I’d love to see is what others can do, and what kind of tools we could build together.</p>
<p>I will now proceed to go on about this at length, starting with a mildly trite statement that I’ll then unpick.</p>
<p>By building pipelines like this, we can speed up reports, maps, dashboards etc, and share them easily (that last link collects a bunch of these in one place).</p>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p><a href="https://github.com/DanOlner/coveredinbees/commits/master/posts/open_econtools/index.qmd">Github file history</a> for previous drafts / cuttings.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Not an endorsement of Valve’s supposedly desk-on-wheels culture or anything similar. As <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2018/jul/30/no-bosses-managers-flat-hierachy-workplace-tech-hollywood">this article explores</a>, structures like this (including some co-ops without explicit rules) can mask a “neo-feudal workplace culture”.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Elephant parable <a href="https://jetzek.wordpress.com/2016/07/19/first-blog-post/">example</a> applied to economics.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>Krugman: “We just don’t see what we can’t formalise”. [citation forgotten!]↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>econ</category>
  <guid>https://coveredinbees.org/posts/open_econtools/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A better world for words</title>
  <link>https://coveredinbees.org/posts/what_happened_to_words/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="other-bits" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="other-bits">OTHER BITS</h2>
<p>Is it possible for us to live happily in seemingly opposed word worlds? I’m thinking of ‘two cultures’ adjacent ideas. Lay out the different aspects, with the ‘adaptive landscapes’ piece prob my best take on it.</p>
<p>What role truth, when language was never built for that? Parallel to the surprising success of maths in physics [where was I reading about that?]</p>
<p>[Cf. legal system where representing opposing realities is built in]</p>
<p>Does it help if we see building sinews of a reality-body as only one facet of how language works? The Balinese case - one can be blind, destroy the other. How to not be blind?</p>
<p>History is absolute mishmash, truth elusive. (<a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2025/oct/01/irish-critics-netflix-series-house-of-guinness-ireland">Example from today</a> re. adding to : “the majority of our popular history is fiction, and quite dangerous fiction at that. We don’t need any more of it”; <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Imagined_Communities">imagined</a> history).</p>
<p>But also then how to have some role for truth? Not a word science likes, of course, there’s no such thing, only current evidence.</p>
<p>All to say, I do have some understanding of the breadth of skies our language allows us to flock together in. That includes understanding the overlap of scientific and state power and its Scottian ability to blot out what it can’t or won’t see.</p>
<p>[“The metaphorical value of this brief account of scientific production forestry is that it illustrates the dangers of dismembering an exceptionally complex and poorly understood set of relations and processes in order to isolate a single element of instrumental value.”]</p>
<p>Cf. what’s close to a perfectly simple example, though it has a lot of layers. Mel Gibson on Joe Rogan: melting ice can’t increase sea levels. Look - when it melts in a glass, it doesn’t go over the glass’ edge, does it? (He looks very pleased with himself here.)</p>
<p>What’s great about this example: it doesn’t have the complexity of some climate science (e.g.&nbsp;the greenhouse effect itself). The actual facts are super-easy to grasp, as John Stewart demonstrated several years earlier.</p>
<p>Yes, it’s known that sea ice melt won’t directly raise sea levels. The issue is ice melting on land going into the oceans.</p>
<p>[That needs its own post.]</p>
</section>
<section id="main" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="main">MAIN</h2>
<p>Words have been getting a bit of a kicking lately. LLMs are looming in everyone’s vision right now. As a few people have put it (e.g.&nbsp;<a href="https://www.spglobal.com/en/research-insights/special-reports/language-modeling-the-fundamentals">here</a>, <a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC11137430/">here</a>, <a href="https://bigwildmindmachine.substack.com/p/the-ny-times-vs-openai">here</a>) humans just lost their monopoly on written language to robots that digested everything ever written, <a href="https://youtu.be/WnTKllDbu5o?t=42">Johnny-5 style</a> (OK, not like that).</p>
<p>But the machinery of language has been radically rewiring for decades, as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Informatics_(disambiguation)">informatics</a> have worked their way into every cell<sup>1</sup>.</p>
<p>Words are the sinews of social and scientific progress. Informatics has already upended older ways these sinews stay supple and strengthen. It’s also opened us up to human-comms equivalents of distributed <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Denial-of-service_attack">denial of service attacks</a> - really nothing more sophisticated than a bunch of people constantly shouting nonsense while others in the room try to think. But it’s been dismayingly effective (<a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-024-74032-0">climate example</a> in Nature), and LLMs may be pouring petrol on that (see e.g.&nbsp;openAI <a href="https://openai.com/index/disrupting-a-covert-iranian-influence-operation/">here</a>, <a href="https://cdn.openai.com/threat-intelligence-reports/influence-and-cyber-operations-an-update_October-2024.pdf">here</a>, also <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/pro-russia-disinformation-campaign-free-ai-tools/">here</a>).</p>
<p>Science (and all knowledge flavours that accrete around universities and other research sites) is a still-surviving modernist structure built up layer by layer through argument and counter-argument<sup>2</sup>, a somehow-functioning mix of reason and chance. Science is struggling. It’s trying to adapt to new tech, or through inertia failing to. It’s shaken by Language DDOS (climate science under attack; ‘sick of experts’; in the U.S., direct authoritarian attacks).</p>
</section>
<section id="bits" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bits">BITS</h2>
<p>This is all deeply political, of course. Authoritarians want to be the sole source of truth, and twist words accordingly. The internet age suits them just fine. But there’s a lot of weird Venn diagram overlap with its apparent opposite, libertarian truthiness<sup>3</sup>. See Peter <a href="https://archive.ph/PvS6B#selection-1971.190-1971.446">Thiel talking about</a> Eric Weinstein’s <a href="https://theportal.wiki/wiki/The_Distributed_Idea_Suppression_Complex_(The_DISC)">term</a>, the ‘Distributed Idea Suppression Complex’. As Thiel puts it, ’The internet has already begun our liberation from the DISC prison… the media organisations, bureaucracies, universities and government-funded NGOs that traditionally delimited public conversation”.</p>
<p>Gramscian cultural hegemony comparisons <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/ThePortal/comments/laigmm/bourdieu_and_the_disc_erics_neologisms/">abound</a>, so that’s nothing new - and I’m not disagreeing that institutions use words to shape reality. What’s striking is DISC’s banality. You can see the same in <a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/elon-musk-twitter-fail-collective-superintelligence-2022-11">Musk’s take on Twitter/X</a>:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“Because it consists of billions of bidirectional interactions per day, Twitter can be thought of as a collective, cybernetic, super-intelligence.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It’s that sufficient-condition “because of” that gets me. Nope, it’s not intelligent because of those interactions. My cup of tea consists of <em>trillions</em> of bidirectional interactions. It has no smarts. This is exactly the same wilful error that Hayekian thinking is often guilty of (more-so than Hayek himself I think) - if you tear things down, a magic fairy dust will ‘emerge’ to replace it. And if you get in the way of that happening, you’re part of the DISC / <a href="https://x.com/search?f=top&amp;q=woke%20mind%20virus%20(from%3Aelonmusk)&amp;src=typed_query">woke mind virus</a>.</p>
<p>Intriguing that the outcome ends up following the grain of authoritarianism - that can be seen in the targets that both attack. Both have implicit theories of truth that seem so opposite: one sole, all-controlling source versus an emergent, everywhere-truth that no-one controls. But the effect on the machinery of knowledge generation is more or less identical. Compare to the famous Arendt quote from <a href="https://idanlandau.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/arendt-truth-and-politics.pdf">Truth and Politics</a>:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“The result of a consistent and total substitution of lies for factual truth is not that the lie will now be accepted as truth and truth be defamed as lies, but that <em>the sense by which we take our bearings in the real world - and the category of truth versus falsehood is among the mental means to this end - is being destroyed</em>.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>That italiced chunk applies equally to both flavours of the right I’m talking about.</p>
<p>Let’s not push the parallel too far. Libertarians aren’t into disappearing people off the street for what they say. But that’s why the childishness of DISC thinking is so frustrating - it seems content to enable its opposite.</p>
<p>So that’s the world that LLMs have entered, that we find ourselves in now. The (actually very useful) idea of emergence is weaponised, paving the way for authoritarians to tediously re-prove Arendt over and over, with added trollfarms. To the extent that DISC thinking has a point - knowledge structures <em>are</em> dominated by white males on computers like me, by wealthy global institutions, of which universities are certainly members - they let the <em>actual</em> point go sailing past: addressing this means exactly the kind of ‘how do we get more voices in here?’ thinking most of them seem to loath.</p>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Strictly, informatics is “the <em>branch of study</em> that deals with the structure, properties, and communication of information and with means of storing or processing information” (<a href="oed_informatics.png">OED def</a>) so it’s wrong, but short. All other options are horrible e.g.&nbsp;<a href="https://mitpress.mit.edu/9780262640428/information-ecologies/">information ecosystem</a> was about the best I could find, not great. Anything better?↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>A Bauman point, that one: modernism - “a ‘total’ order to be erected floor by floor in a protracted, consistent, purpose-guided effort of labour.” (Liquid modernity)↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>this overlap shows up in other arguments about ‘authoritarian nenoliberalism’ going back to Thatcher/Pinochet/<a href="https://coveredinbees.org.archived.website/node/165.html">Allende/Stafford</a>, but this language stuff is possibly a different variation, not sure.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>sos</category>
  <guid>https://coveredinbees.org/posts/what_happened_to_words/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
