<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>COVEREDINBEES / A hive of TLDR &amp; villainy</title>
<link>https://coveredinbees.org/</link>
<atom:link href="https://coveredinbees.org/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>A hive of TLDR and villainy</description>
<generator>quarto-1.7.33</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 23:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>What happened to words?</title>
  <link>https://coveredinbees.org/posts/what_happened_to_words_DRAFT/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<ul>
<li>So I’ve had a good rant, and linked different styles of the right to the same undermining of our ability to use words to form stable, supple, strengthening sinews. Next bit needs to be: so what? Where do we go from here? It might be enough for a post just to ask that question and come back to it later?</li>
</ul>
<section id="main" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="main">MAIN</h2>
<p>Words have been getting a bit of a kicking lately. LLMs are looming in everyone’s vision right now. As a few people have put it (e.g.&nbsp;<a href="https://www.spglobal.com/en/research-insights/special-reports/language-modeling-the-fundamentals">here</a>, <a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC11137430/">here</a>, <a href="https://bigwildmindmachine.substack.com/p/the-ny-times-vs-openai">here</a>) humans just lost their monopoly on written language to robots that digested everything ever written, <a href="https://youtu.be/WnTKllDbu5o?t=42">Johnny-5 style</a> (OK, not like that).</p>
<p>But the machinery of language has been radically rewiring for decades, as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Informatics_(disambiguation)">informatics</a> have worked their way into every cell<sup>1</sup>.</p>
<p>Words are the sinews of social and scientific progress. Informatics has already upended older ways these sinews stay supple and strengthen. It’s also opened us up to human-comms equivalents of distributed <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Denial-of-service_attack">denial of service attacks</a> - really nothing more sophisticated than a bunch of people constantly shouting nonsense while others in the room try to think. But it’s been dismayingly effective (<a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-024-74032-0">climate example</a> in Nature), and LLMs may be pouring petrol on that (see e.g.&nbsp;openAI <a href="https://openai.com/index/disrupting-a-covert-iranian-influence-operation/">here</a>, <a href="https://cdn.openai.com/threat-intelligence-reports/influence-and-cyber-operations-an-update_October-2024.pdf">here</a>, also <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/pro-russia-disinformation-campaign-free-ai-tools/">here</a>).</p>
<p>Science (and all other knowledge flavours that accrete around universities) is a still-surviving modernist structure built up layer by layer through argument and counter-argument<sup>2</sup>, a somehow-functioning mix of reason and chance. Science is struggling. It’s trying to adapt to new tech, or through inertia failing to. It’s shaken by Language DDOS (climate science under attack; ‘sick of experts’; in the U.S., direct authoritarian attacks).</p>
<p>This is all deeply political, of course. Authoritarians want to be the sole source of truth, and twist words accordingly. The internet age suits them just fine. But there’s a lot of weird Venn diagram overlap with its apparent opposite, libertarian truthiness<sup>3</sup>. See Peter <a href="https://archive.ph/PvS6B#selection-1971.190-1971.446">Thiel talking about</a> Eric Weinstein’s <a href="https://theportal.wiki/wiki/The_Distributed_Idea_Suppression_Complex_(The_DISC)">term</a>, the ‘Distributed Idea Suppression Complex’. As Thiel puts it, ’The internet has already begun our liberation from the DISC prison… the media organisations, bureaucracies, universities and government-funded NGOs that traditionally delimited public conversation”.</p>
<p>Gramscian cultural hegemony comparisons <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/ThePortal/comments/laigmm/bourdieu_and_the_disc_erics_neologisms/">abound</a>, so that’s nothing new - and I’m not disagreeing that institutions use words to shape reality. What’s striking is DISC’s banality. You can see the same in <a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/elon-musk-twitter-fail-collective-superintelligence-2022-11">Musk’s take on Twitter/X</a>:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“Because it consists of billions of bidirectional interactions per day, Twitter can be thought of as a collective, cybernetic, super-intelligence.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It’s that sufficient-condition “because of” that gets me. Nope, it’s not intelligent because of those interactions. My cup of tea consists of <em>trillions</em> of bidirectional interactions. It has no smarts. This is exactly the same wilful error that Hayekian thinking is often guilty of (more-so than Hayek himself I think) - if you tear things down, a magic fairy dust will ‘emerge’ to replace it. And if you get in the way of that happening, you’re part of the DISC / <a href="https://x.com/search?f=top&amp;q=woke%20mind%20virus%20(from%3Aelonmusk)&amp;src=typed_query">woke mind virus</a>.</p>
<p>Intriguing that the outcome ends up following the grain of authoritarianism - that can be seen in the targets that both attack. Both have implicit theories of truth that seem so opposite: one sole, all-controlling source versus an emergent, everywhere-truth that no-one controls. But the effect on the machinery of knowledge generation is more or less identical. Compare to the famous Arendt quote from <a href="https://idanlandau.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/arendt-truth-and-politics.pdf">Truth and Politics</a>:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“The result of a consistent and total substitution of lies for factual truth is not that the lie will now be accepted as truth and truth be defamed as lies, but that <em>the sense by which we take our bearings in the real world - and the category of truth versus falsehood is among the mental means to this end - is being destroyed</em>.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>That italiced chunk applies equally to both flavours of the right I’m talking about.</p>
<p>Let’s not push the parallel too far. Libertarians aren’t into disappearing people off the street for what they say. But that’s why the childishness of DISC thinking is so frustrating - it seems content to enable its opposite.</p>
<p>So that’s the world that LLMs have entered, that we find ourselves in now. The (actually very useful) idea of emergence is weaponised, paving the way for authoritarians to tediously re-prove Arendt over and over, with added trollfarms. To the extent that DISC thinking has a point - knowledge structures <em>are</em> dominated by white males on computers like me, by wealthy global institutions, of which universities are certainly members - they let the <em>actual</em> point go sailing past: addressing this means exactly the kind of ‘how do we get more voices in here?’ thinking most of them seem to loath.</p>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Strictly, informatics is “the <em>branch of study</em> that deals with the structure, properties, and communication of information and with means of storing or processing information” (<a href="oed_informatics.png">OED def</a>) so it’s wrong, but short. All other options are horrible e.g.&nbsp;<a href="https://mitpress.mit.edu/9780262640428/information-ecologies/">information ecosystem</a> was about the best I could find, not great. Anything better?↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>A Bauman point, that one: modernism - “a ‘total’ order to be erected floor by floor in a protracted, consistent, purpose-guided effort of labour.” (Liquid modernity)↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>this overlap shows up in other arguments about ‘authoritarian nenoliberalism’ going back to Thatcher/Pinochet/<a href="https://coveredinbees.org.archived.website/node/165.html">Allende/Stafford</a>, but this language stuff is possibly a different variation, not sure.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>draft</category>
  <guid>https://coveredinbees.org/posts/what_happened_to_words_DRAFT/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Go on, now it’s live, just one last test to make sure.</title>
  <link>https://coveredinbees.org/posts/OneLastRSSTest_DRAFT/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>This would be the draft doc.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>draft</category>
  <guid>https://coveredinbees.org/posts/OneLastRSSTest_DRAFT/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>21st Century peer review</title>
  <link>https://coveredinbees.org/posts/peer_review_C21st/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>21st century peer review, how to make it work. Separate out all the different types e.g.&nbsp;tiny incremental technical progress in papers (some patenting to get IP) is a very different world to e.g.&nbsp;open urban work. Structures vastly different. Or exploratory thought pieces vs medical testing. Put in context of what we do not want to happen: what happened with supposed ‘citizen science’ for climate change, which was just idiots shouting “I am Galileo!” Some but not all of those oil-funded, some but not all of those with raging Dunning-Kruger. (Cf. <a href="https://web.stanford.edu/~fukamit/schwartz-2008.pdf">constructive stupidity</a>.)</p>
<p>Other random points:</p>
<ul>
<li>Now equivalent of DDOS attack via LLMs…?</li>
<li>New tools? Github as way to produce, review, edit in a fully open and traceable way?</li>
<li>The ostensible goal: continue to increase real knowledge a slice at a time. But what role does or could knowledge systems play in this? Back to the original “how does science / how does knowledge growth <em>actually</em> work vs how we imagine it should”. Overlaps with the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Demarcation_problem">demarcation problem</a> / shows up in arguments around <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scientism">scientism</a>. (That’s a really great wikipedia article on the subject).</li>
</ul>



 ]]></description>
  <category>draft</category>
  <guid>https://coveredinbees.org/posts/peer_review_C21st/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Why 1st drafts?</title>
  <link>https://coveredinbees.org/posts/why_sfd/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>On this site, you’ve got the option of subscribing to <a href="https://danolner.github.io/coveredinbees/index.xml">first drafts</a>, as well as <a href="https://danolner.github.io/coveredinbees/index-final.xml">final drafts</a> (RSS links).</p>
<p>The email subscription option defaults to final pieces only - tick the ‘1st draft’ box you want in on everything.</p>
<p>Why on Earth would I be giving you the option to read 1st drafts? Isn’t life short enough already?</p>
<ul>
<li>I’m using “1st draft” here to mean: the start of an idea or topic, in a post that I’ll continue to edit, ramble in, add links and connected thoughts, keeping it all in one place and regularly <a href="https://github.com/DanOlner/coveredinbees">pushing to github</a>.</li>
<li>In “1st drafts” I’ll try and lay out what I think the questions are and get some first points down. These may just be snippets that never go anywhere or they may grow. Though it absolutely will include <a href="https://wrd.as.uky.edu/sites/default/files/1-Shitty%20First%20Drafts.pdf">shitty first drafts</a> along the way, the point is to get stuff out there, experiment with it and let it grow.</li>
<li>This is also part of having <strong>more control and ownership</strong> as well as using a structure that <strong>leaves an accountability trail</strong> by being as open as possible. Everything here is on my own machine as well as <a href="https://github.com/DanOlner/coveredinbees">stored on Github</a> (admittedly, owned by Microsoft). If anyone so desires - why would you, that’d be mad, but if you <em>wanted</em> to- you could look at the history of any file (<a href="https://github.com/DanOlner/coveredinbees/commits/master/posts/why_sfd/index.qmd">here’s</a> this one’s) and see what’s changed (e.g.&nbsp;a <a href="https://github.com/DanOlner/coveredinbees/commit/78788d0ca8ecbc5e46305a3849a196bf17e16165#diff-b4ac3c529b00f3e9f57376c3dd67f1700d6c2c70e2f62874c67ae7307faf0dae">recent commit difference</a>). You could even sign up to github and <a href="https://github.com/DanOlner/coveredinbees/issues/new?permalink=https%3A%2F%2Fgithub.com%2FDanOlner%2Fcoveredinbees%2Fblob%2F4426c86ade5bd504d01a72e2ab3df02becc26a5d%2Fposts%2Fwhy_sfd%2Findex.qmd%23L1">add comments</a>.<sup>1</sup></li>
</ul>
<p>What I like about github is all those things I mentioned above - openness, visibility, accountability, ownership. (Shhh about Microsoft, shhhh.) But in these systems, one can also see ways to make knowledge in a distributed way, in a place where there’s enough of a level of control to balance collaboration and safety. I can warm my bones late at night imagining that, in some tiny way, I’m contributing to a <a href="../what_happened_to_words_DRAFT">better world for words</a>.</p>
<p>It’s possible. Places <em>already exist</em> where this has worked. Wikipedia is straight-up brilliant (entirely unsurprising people like Musk should <a href="muskpedia.png">attack it</a>), well-designed tech channelling collaboration into incremental improvements while keeping the idiots at bay.</p>
<p>Also - why write when you can instead spend far too long setting up complex writing systems? The <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/quotes/comments/btuvib/i_am_rarely_happier_than_when_spending_an_entire">Douglas Adams principle of programming</a>:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“I am rarely happier than when spending an entire day programming my computer to perform automatically a task that would otherwise take me a good ten seconds to do by hand.”</p>
</blockquote>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Not quite as ridiculous as it sounds - github is one of the few collab platforms I’ve found that works across both universities and UK public bodies, where often many websites are blocked (I presume because it’s Microsoft owned).↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>final</category>
  <guid>https://coveredinbees.org/posts/why_sfd/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 17 Aug 2025 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
