<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>COVEREDINBEES / A hive of TLDR &amp; villainy</title>
<link>https://danolner.github.io/coveredinbees/#category=draft</link>
<atom:link href="https://danolner.github.io/coveredinbees/index-draft.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>A hive of TLDR and villainy</description>
<generator>quarto-1.5.57</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Sun, 17 Aug 2025 23:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>What an SFD looks like. Why do it here?</title>
  <dc:creator>Dan Olner</dc:creator>
  <link>https://danolner.github.io/coveredinbees/posts/why_sfd/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>You’ve got the option of subscribing to <a href="https://danolner.github.io/coveredinbees/index.xml">first drafts</a> here, as well as <a href="https://danolner.github.io/coveredinbees/index-final.xml">final drafts</a> (either with those RSS links, or email subscription via Buttondown). Why? Short version, followed by longer ramble.</p>
<ul>
<li>I want to build in the idea that all writing/thinking starts out a mess. You have to allow yourself the <a href="https://wrd.as.uky.edu/sites/default/files/1-Shitty%20First%20Drafts.pdf">shitty first drafts</a>. Arguably no-one wants to see that mess - why not skip to the end?</li>
<li>That’s always possible, but being open - and doing that using open platforms like github - lets in some chances for experimentation. More on that below.</li>
</ul>
<p>OK, the longer version.</p>
<p>Words have been getting a bit of a kicking lately. Looming in everyone’s vision right now is (as a few people have put it e.g.&nbsp;<a href="https://www.spglobal.com/en/research-insights/special-reports/language-modeling-the-fundamentals">here</a>, <a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC11137430/">here</a>, <a href="https://bigwildmindmachine.substack.com/p/the-ny-times-vs-openai">here</a>) that humans just lost their monopoly on coherent written language.</p>
<p>But while everyone argues about just how radical the LLM shift is, the machinery of language has been shifting around us for a good while longer. Who knows where it might land after all this. It’s obvious to state but words are/were the sinews of scientific progress, a still-surviving modernist structure built up layer by layer through argument and counter-argument<sup>1</sup>, a somehow-functioning mix of reason and chance. Human knowledge <em>grew</em>.</p>
<p>It’s still growing, but <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Informatics_(disambiguation)">informatics</a> is upending a lot of the ways it can grow, and it’s opened us up to the language equivalents of distributed <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Denial-of-service_attack">denial of service attacks</a>.</p>
<section id="cuttinz" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="cuttinz">CUTTINZ</h2>
<p>Words have been getting a bit of a kicking lately. As a few people have noted, humans just lost their monopoly on being able to produce coherent written language…</p>
<p>Is that a good way to start this? Christ, the first paragraph. Never start there. Do the first paragraph <em>last</em>. Obviously. Why is that so hard to remember? Anyway, let’s try that again and explain what I’m trying to do here.</p>
<p>Err. Writing is an interative process. You have to allow yourself the <a href="https://wrd.as.uky.edu/sites/default/files/1-Shitty%20First%20Drafts.pdf">shitty first drafts</a>. For mere humans, SFDs are not optional - plural, for there can be many, many of them before writing approaches anything like coherent, before it can appear like you actually thought up a structured argument in the first place, before you even <em>know</em> what you might be trying to say.</p>
<p>And then something about how we can lean into the SFD, make that process open, and all the reasons that’s a good thing. Or could be a good thing.</p>
<p><img src="https://danolner.github.io/coveredinbees/posts/why_sfd/sfd.png" class="img-fluid"></p>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>A Bauman point, that one: modernism - “a ‘total’ order to be erected floor by floor in a protracted, consistent, purpose-guided effort of labour.” (Liquid modernity)↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>draft</category>
  <guid>https://danolner.github.io/coveredinbees/posts/why_sfd/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 17 Aug 2025 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
