<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>COVEREDINBEES / A hive of TLDR &amp; villainy</title>
<link>https://danolner.github.io/coveredinbees/</link>
<atom:link href="https://danolner.github.io/coveredinbees/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>A hive of TLDR and villainy</description>
<generator>quarto-1.5.57</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 23:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Does draft / final RSS sub work?</title>
  <dc:creator>Dan Olner</dc:creator>
  <link>https://danolner.github.io/coveredinbees/posts/testdraft/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Final stage!</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>final</category>
  <guid>https://danolner.github.io/coveredinbees/posts/testdraft/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>What an SFD looks like. Why do it here?</title>
  <dc:creator>Dan Olner</dc:creator>
  <link>https://danolner.github.io/coveredinbees/posts/why_sfd/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Words have been getting a bit of a kicking lately. As a few poeple have noted, humans just lost their monopoly on being able to produce coherent written language…</p>
<p>Is that a good way to start this? Christ, the first paragraph. Never start there. Do the first paragraph <em>last</em>. Obviously. Why is that so hard to remember? Anyway, let’s try that again and explain what I’m trying to do here.</p>
<p>Err. Writing is an interative process. You have to allow yourself the <a href="https://wrd.as.uky.edu/sites/default/files/1-Shitty%20First%20Drafts.pdf">shitty first drafts</a>. For mere humans, SFDs are not optional - plural, for there can be many, many of them before writing approaches anything like coherent, before it can appear like you actually thought up a structured argument in the first place, before you even <em>know</em> what you might be trying to say.</p>
<p>And then something about how we can lean into the SFD, make that process open, and all the reasons that’s a good thing. Or could be a good thing.</p>
<p><img src="https://danolner.github.io/coveredinbees/posts/why_sfd/excel_hell2.png" class="img-fluid"></p>



<p>subscribe.html</p> ]]></description>
  <category>draft</category>
  <guid>https://danolner.github.io/coveredinbees/posts/why_sfd/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 17 Aug 2025 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>21st Century peer review</title>
  <dc:creator>Dan Olner</dc:creator>
  <link>https://danolner.github.io/coveredinbees/posts/peer_review_C21st/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>21st century peer review, how to make it work. Separate out all the different types e.g.&nbsp;tiny incremental technical progress in papers (some patenting to get IP) is a very different world to e.g.&nbsp;open urban work. Structures vastly different. Or exploratory thought pieces vs medical testing. Put in context of what we do not want to happen: what happened with supposed ‘citizen science’ for climate change, which was just idiots shouting “I am Galileo!” Some but not all of those oil-funded, some but not all of those with raging Dunning-Kruger. (Cf. <a href="https://web.stanford.edu/~fukamit/schwartz-2008.pdf">constructive stupidity</a>.)</p>
<p>Other random points:</p>
<ul>
<li>Now equivalent of DDOS attack via LLMs…?</li>
<li>New tools? Github as way to produce, review, edit in a fully open and traceable way?</li>
<li>The ostensible goal: continue to increase real knowledge a slice at a time. But what role does or could knowledge systems play in this? Back to the original “how does science / how does knowledge growth <em>actually</em> work vs how we imagine it should”. Overlaps with the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Demarcation_problem">demarcation problem</a> / shows up in arguments around <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scientism">scientism</a>. (That’s a really great wikipedia article on the subject).</li>
</ul>



 ]]></description>
  <category>draft</category>
  <guid>https://danolner.github.io/coveredinbees/posts/peer_review_C21st/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 17 Aug 2025 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
